‫I hope you all are here because you ‫know that there's a quiz next week.
‫So what is this quiz about? ‫It's about what we've talked about ‫so far in this class, of course.
‫What is this class about? ‫Someone remember ‫from my first lecture,
‫what is this class about? What are ‫we trying to test you in this class? ‫Algorithms.
‫Also data structures, that's ‫what the first part of this is.
‫But really, it's to get you to solve ‫computational problems. That's the first thing.
‫Be able to argue to someone else ‫that you actually did solve it. ‫It's correct.
‫That you chose something that's better than other things, that it's ‫efficient, and that you can communicate those things to other people.
‫Those are my big four that I ‫try to get you guys to internalize.
‫And so that's what our quizzes ‫are going to try to evaluate you on.
‫And so aside from some nitty gritty kind of ‫stuff that we do at the beginning of the term,
‫like talking about our ‫model of computation, ‫our model, ‫and asymptotics, asymptotics, is
‫that right? ‫Recurrences.
‫Aside from these kind of basics, we ‫kind of delve straight into algorithms.
‫These are kind of like almost definitions. ‫We don't rely on these things very much.
‫I mean, we rely on ‫these things all the time,
‫like the mathematics that we use to talk about things. How can we even say how long this stuff takes unless we can reason, we can abstract away ‫that this stuff is not on a real computer. This is kind of in our minds in a computer. And we're reasoning about these things based on the number of
‫constant time operations
‫this magical computer might have, which is a pretty good representation ‫of any of the computers you have for certain assumptions.
‫I mean, there's not a lot of problem ‫set questions we had you talk about. ‫But these things,
‫like specifically, usually they ‫were part of some other problem.
‫You had to describe the running time of this thing. ‫And you might have had to solve a recurrence.
‫And you might use master ‫theorem, that kind of thing.
‫Or you use asymptotics all the time. Or you need to remember in our model, oh, it kind of matters how big of an integer ‫I can store and do arithmetic on in constant time. So for that pset 3 question you had at the end of the coding question,
‫you wanted to hash things. And you need to argue that those things fit in ‫a constant number of words so that that could be done in constant time.
‫A lot of you guys ‫found canonicalizations,
‫basically mapping to things ‫that were exponentially large,
‫so maybe multiplying a product of primes or something ‫like that. And that would not be a good representation.
‫So these things come up, but they're not ‫the main focus of the problems we solve.
‫What are the main focus of the? How do we solve a computational ‫problem in this class? I kind of gave you two ways
‫at the beginning of the ‫term. Do you guys remember? ‫We can solve how to solve
‫a computational problem. ‫One's the hard way. ‫One's the easy way.
‫Brute force. JASON ‫KUO - Brute force?
‫OK, so you're describing to me a ‫technique for making your own algorithm.
‫I can just design my new algorithm from scratch. One way I could do that is ‫brute force it, look at all the possible outputs and see which one works.
‫Or I could reduce to something like divide and conquer or something like ‫that. That's generally a hard thing to do to make your own algorithm.
‫That's why we don't ask you ‫to do it a lot in this class.
‫It's an 046 kind of thing. So the ‫first thing you could do is write
‫design new algorithm ‫from scratch. ‫Usually, it's not from scratch.
‫Usually, you're reducing to some kind of algorithmic design paradigm ‫that you've maybe heard of. You'll talk a lot more about it in 046.
‫And at the end of this term, when ‫we talk about dynamic programming.
‫But generally, that's ‫a hard thing to do. ‫You're trying to think ‫of a recursive algorithm.
‫You're trying to prove that it's ‫correct, all these nitty gritty.
‫We have actually, throughout ‫the class in lectures,
‫have been showing you the algorithms. But we're not really expecting you ‫to make those algorithms. What are we expecting you to do most of the time?
‫Yeah? ‫To reduce it to a problem ‫that we showed you how to solve.
‫I'm going to say thing here. But really, what I mean is an algorithm ‫that we've taught you to basically here, reduce to a known thing.
‫No ‫to ‫known thing. ‫Usually, that means there's ‫a problem or an interface
‫that we've given you.
‫And in general, we've shown you multiple ‫different ways to solve that problem or interface.
‫So we've shown you many ‫ways on how to sort things.
‫And we've shown you many ways on how ‫to implement sequence and set interfaces. ‫Remember?
‫And a lot of times, the types of problems that we're asking you to ‫do is to just use as a black box some of the things that we did.
‫But you need, as a programmer, as a ‫computer scientist, you need to tell
‫me when I should use what when. ‫Yeah? Could you clarify what ‫you mean by use as a black box?
‫JASON KUO - Mm -hmm. Use ‫as a black box. Exactly. ‫Right.
‫So this is a phrase that I use and a ‫lot of people in computer science use. ‫It's basically,
‫you import a library ‫into your code.
‫What do I have? I have kind of an API. ‫I have a way to interact with that code.
‫I don't actually know what's ‫going on inside of that library.
‫I'm using it as a black ‫box. It's opaque to me.
‫I cannot look inside what the I mean, I actually ‫probably could look inside what their code is.
‫The thing that makes it useful to me is that it has this useful API that ‫I trust it to do the things that you told me that it was going to do.
‫And so there's kind of,
‫I'm going to jump around a little bit here, ‫actually, because that's a great question. ‫So here,
‫I think of there's kind of three different types of problems that we talk about ‫that we give you in this class. You might have seen this on the problem set.
‫I like to categorize them ‫into kind of three different ‫categories here. ‫One is,
‫you kind of have to understand the internals of a data structure ‫and algorithm that we know. You have to be able to look inside and,
‫I don't know, given a node in a ‫balanced binary search tree, an AVL tree,
‫how can I do a rotation? ‫Or how do I do an insert?
‫Or something about the ‫structure of this thing, ‫a binary.
‫Heap, where are the top k things in a max ‫binary heap, which is on your problem set?
‫Those things require me to very much not black ‫box these data structures. It's a white box.
‫I need to know what's inside of that to answer that question. ‫I need to know about the internals of that data structure.
‫And there are other types ‫of problems where it's like,
‫oh, I don't need to know what the internals of this data ‫structure is. I can just operate with knowledge of the API.
‫And try to hook it into ‫the problem that I need.
‫And that's what I call ‫a reduction type problem.
‫This is like, how does the core material ‫we presented to you in lecture work?
‫This is like, how do I ‫apply that core material? ‫And
‫harder than both of those things is what I might call a modification type of ‫problem. These aren't really good names. I came up with these this morning.
‫But it's trying to get ‫at the idea here that
‫it's possible that you kind of need to know what the API is. And you kind ‫of need to know what's going on inside to be able to answer the problem.
‫Things like adapting a ‫divide and conquer algorithm. ‫Or instead of using ‫a dynamic array ‫that
‫has extra space on one end, maybe I have to put ‫extra space in the middle or something like that.
‫I'm adapting something that was from ‫the core material. It's pretty close.
‫But I have to modify it in some way. ‫Augmentation. I have to take the vanilla
‫set AVL tree that I might have given you and put some other ‫property on the nodes. And you need to tell me how to maintain that.
‫How can I compute that subtree ‫property from its children? ‫Does that make sense?
‫So this is the ‫harder of the things.
‫If you can identify which one of these a problem that you ‫look at on an exam fit under, maybe that can help you kind
‫of conceptualize ‫what should I use. ‫For a reduction type problem,
‫we're going to talk ‫about this in a second. ‫But a lot of times, ‫it's useful to reduce it
‫to a problem or an interface rather ‫than an algorithm or a data structure. ‫What does that mean?
‫If I can solve the problem by ‫saying reducing to sorting, I
‫can argue to you that that algorithm is ‫correct. I just use sorting as a black box.
‫No, it might not be efficient. ‫My choice of sorting ‫algorithm that I chose matters
‫for efficiency. ‫But for correctness, ‫it doesn't matter.
‫For a data structures problem, I might reduce to using two set data ‫structures and a sequence data structure or something like that.
‫But
‫it will be correct if I reduce it to those things. I ‫can define the operations in terms of those interfaces.
‫I don't have to make that choice ‫until I talk about running time, ‫until I talk about efficiency.
‫And the name of the game ‫on the quiz to get points
‫is we can't give you points for an incorrect ‫algorithm or something that's pretty close to correct.
‫And we can't give you full points unless the correct algorithm you give us is efficient ‫and that you've argued things like correctness and running time and things like that.
‫Your algorithm could be correct ‫and efficient, but you analyze ‫the running time incorrectly.
‫So we mark your ‫points off for there.
‫What you do is you present us ‫with an inefficient algorithm,
‫and then you analyze the running time as if ‫it's the target running time that we gave you.
‫That's bad on two fronts. ‫So try not to fall ‫into these traps.
‫So some general test -taking strategies ‫when you're looking at your quiz.
‫I really strongly urge you to read through the entire exam before you ‫start because some of the problems will be easier for you than others.
‫And if you're trying to ‫maximize points on here, ‫as all of you, I'm ‫sure, are trying to do,
‫it's useful to make that initial pass through the ‫problems to see which ones are easiest for you.
‫And then you can tackle them in the ‫order in which you have confidence.
‫Now, in actuality, the average on, say, quiz 1 ‫of this class tends to be around, I don't know,
‫between a 60 and an 80. I ‫don't think it's ever been 80. ‫But it's not 100. ‫Right?
‫So doing 50 % of ‫the problems well
‫is probably going to be better for you in terms of time management and those kinds of things than ‫attempting all of the problems and not doing great on any of them in terms of point management.
‫In computer science, you have to be pretty ‫close to a correct answer to get points. ‫Right?
‫It basically needs to be ‫almost correct or you don't get.
‫If you've seen how your problem sets are being graded, ‫sometimes our problem set graders make mistakes.
‫Sometimes they give you points ‫for an incorrect solution. ‫Right?
‫It's really on you to take a look at your problem sets that you gave us and our ‫solutions that we gave you. We spent a lot of time writing good solutions for you guys.
‫You need to make sure ‫that you know the material.
‫Don't come up to us at the ‫end of an exam and say, oh, I
‫said the same thing on my problem set. It was ‫marked correct. And you guys marked it wrong.
‫Well, yeah. The staff knows a little bit more about algorithms ‫than your graders on your problem sets. And we grade your exams.
‫So unfortunately, that's not an excuse. ‫Right? It's on you to know the material. ‫Yep?
‫So are most of the ‫problems on the exams are
‫multiple part things where we need to have a good understanding and do the first few parts right ‫in order to get even partial credit on the other parts? Or is it like it's a shorter thing?
‫The question is, ‫are questions ‫built on top of each ‫other
‫so that you're kind of at a wall if you miss the first part? We try not to design exams ‫that way. You can actually take a look at the practice exam that's already been posted.
‫Our problems tend to ‫be self -contained.
‫And if they are multiple parts, ‫the parts are usually independent.
‫Usually, you don't need to have ‫done A correctly in order to do B.
‫And that's how our problem ‫sets try to be written as well. ‫Right? For your last
‫decoding question on PSAT 4, you had this problem ‫where you had to design this data structure.
‫Right? ‫But C said, use that as a black box, ‫essentially, and solve the problem. ‫Right?
‫So you actually ‫don't need to show. ‫We've given you this interface. ‫Right?
‫You can just use that interface to be ‫able to answer C, the algorithms question,
‫without even solving the data structures ‫question correctly. Does that make sense?
‫And actually, that was the algorithms question was ‫the easier one there, I think, from what I remember.
‫Yeah? ‫Do we have to write ‫code on the exam?
‫JASON KUO - Do you have ‫to write code on the exam?
‫I've never given an exam ‫where you've had to write code.
‫I have written exams ‫where you have to read code. ‫OK? ‫So pseudocode or Python. ‫Right?
‫Since Python's a ‫prerequisite, for this class,
‫it's completely fair game that we give you small snippets of ‫Python code. And you have to be able to understand what's going on.
‫Yeah? ‫You said amortization ‫under the modification part.
‫So does that mean if we're ‫using an amortized run time? ‫JASON KUO - Yeah. ‫What I mean here,
‫amortization certainly ‫appears in here or here. ‫Right? These kinds of things.
‫Oftentimes, if I'm using a dynamic array, if I'm ‫using a binary heap, if I'm using a hash table,
‫amortization will appear here in our running times for those dynamic operations. What I mean here in ‫amortization, I mean if I'm asking you to generalize something that we've done, like with dynamic arrays, where
‫instead of adding additional space at the end, I'm putting additional space in the middle or at ‫the beginning or something like that, and you're having to do some kind of amortized analysis.
‫Now, often, it's ‫unnecessary to do this.
‫When we talked about a problem where we did do our own amortized ‫analysis of making a double -ended deck, I mean a double -ended queue,
‫you could actually solve it by ‫reducing to using two dynamic arrays.
‫So there's a lot ‫of ways in which
‫you could reduce to using things, but you might ‫have to do some additional bookkeeping at the end.
‫But what this is saying ‫is that these are more,
‫you're not using things as a black box. You're changing something ‫about the boxes that we gave you. Right? Does that make sense?
‫Yeah?
‫If you tell us to write an algorithm that does something like O log n time, and we can think only of an algorithm ‫that does something inefficiently like O log n time, then is there any point in writing that? JASON KUO - Sure.
‫So let's actually ‫move on for a second. ‫There's ‫I'm going to answer ‫your question very soon.
‫OK. ‫But I'm going to get ‫to it in a second. ‫OK?
‫If I don't answer that question ‫in five minutes, please let me know.
‫OK. So the first thing when I'm approaching a problem on the ‫exam, I might try to ask some questions about the problem.
‫OK? ‫It's going to help me ‫decide what to use. Right? ‫Different than your ‫problem sets. Right?
‫Your problem sets.
‫So basically, what do you use is what did ‫we talk about in lecture that week? Right?
‫On a quiz, you have eight ‫lectures that you've talked about.
‫And so this is going to be a harder thing for you to do. Right? Because you don't know which of the eight ‫lecture material is going to apply to this problem. And it could be a combination of them, actually. Right?
‫And so I'm trying to give you ways ‫of answering that question faster. OK?
‫So is this a mechanical reduction or a modification type problem? That's just going to help ‫me determine kind of the difficulty level of what this is. I might not be able to answer it.
‫Right? But it can give you a ‫sense for what kind of problem it is.
‫Is this a problem about ‫data structures sorting both? ‫Right? ‫If it's about data structures,
‫do I need to support sequence type operations? Do ‫I need to store an extrinsic order on something?
‫Or is it a thing where I care about what the objects ‫are? I'm trying to look things up by what they are.
‫Right? ‫Or maybe both.
‫Or maybe some combination. Right? If I have a bunch of different types of keys that I ‫might want to query on, I might have to use at least two set type of data structures.
‫Right? You could get very ‫complicated with these things.
‫But putting it in terms of, well, I'm going to ‫need to do this kind of operation on these names,
‫then I can think, oh, I need to set data structure there. I'll think about how to implement ‫that later. Should I use a hash table? Should I use a sorted array? Should I use a AVL tree?
‫Right?
‫But thinking about it first at the abstract level of, I need ‫to set data structure here can help you compartmentalize
‫correctness versus efficiency. ‫Does that make sense? ‫OK.
‫If you're stuck, ‫this is your question. ‫If you're stuck,
‫write down a correct ‫algorithm that's inefficient.
‫Right? We can give you points for a correct algorithm ‫that's inefficient. At least it's a correct algorithm.
‫It's better than other things. ‫Right? ‫Now, if it's exponential time,
‫you might be limited to, like,
‫10 % or 20 % of the points. Right? But if it's ‫a log factor worse or a linear factor worse,
‫maybe that's OK. Right? ‫On a data structures problem, if ‫any operation takes order n time,
‫that's probably not going to give you a lot of points because the ‫whole point of the data structure is to make those operations fast.
‫Right? ‫But if it solves the problem, ‫you'll get some points. ‫You won't get zero points. ‫Yeah?
‫Will we get any ‫questions that are,
‫how fast can you make this, make this as fast as ‫possible? JASON KUO - Yeah. So a lot of times, we'll say,
‫give us an efficient algorithm. ‫OK. It's like,
‫whoa, I don't know if it's efficient or not. Well, that just ‫means that faster running times are going to give you more points.
‫OK? ‫So in questions like that, ‫it's mostly trying ‫to play this game of,
‫usually, we'll put an efficient one not in terms of a data structure ‫because, usually, the data structures problem, it's important
‫in your implementation that ‫these data structure ‫operations be fast.
‫And we want to tell you ‫how fast it is. Right? ‫So data structures ‫questions, in general,
‫there's usually a ‫trade -off between
‫the running times of these different operations. And it's really important ‫how they relate to each other. And so for data structures problem,
‫it's kind of about ‫getting those running times.
‫OK? With an algorithms problem, where we ask you to do ‫one thing, right, and we try to do as fast as possible,
‫try to get linear time.
‫Right? Most of the time, you can't get better than linear time if you have to read the ‫entire input at some point. Right? Like if I want to find the things in my data. Right?
‫And if you can't think ‫of a linear time algorithm,
‫think of an n squared thing or ‫think of an n log n thing. Right? ‫Maybe
‫that's a little hard for you ‫guys to think of right now. ‫Right? But
‫that's why I'm saying, start with any correct ‫algorithm. And then maybe you can optimize.
‫Maybe you can use a better data structure to ‫make it more efficient. Does that make sense?
‫Any other questions? ‫OK. ‫Moving right along. ‫OK. ‫Here's some downsides. ‫Right? ‫OK.
‫If you find yourself doing ‫one of these three things,
‫take a step back. You're ‫probably doing something wrong. ‫OK?
‫So question yourself if you're ‫trying to compute decimals, ‫rationals, or real numbers.
‫I can't store those things on a, I mean, ‫I can store decimals to finite precision.
‫Right? But if you're ‫doing finite precision, ‫you might as well round,
‫like multiply your numbers by that ‫fixed precision and deal with integers. ‫Right?
‫We only have taught you how to deal ‫with integers in this class. Right?
‫We haven't even shown you how to efficiently ‫compute on rationals and real numbers. We have
‫told you if you have a denominator and a ‫numerator of a fraction, I can take two fractions
‫and compare them in constant ‫time by doing cross multiplication.
‫But if I'm trying to ‫actually do this division ‫to arbitrary precision, ‫that's not happy.
‫Right? Because I can't even represent that on my ‫computer in finite number of decimal points for some
‫of these things. ‫Right?
‫If you're trying to use radix sort ‫for every answer, it's probably wrong. ‫Right?
‫One of the things that we ‫try to do on our quizzes,
‫right, we're not just giving ‫you a bunch of problems randomly. ‫Right?
‫We probably are making problems that ‫cover the material in some way. Right?
‫We do want to test you ‫on all of the things. ‫Right?
‫And so if you find that you're using the ‫same thing four or five times on the exam,
‫that might be a sign that
‫you're using it too many times. It's not always the case. Right? Sometimes hashing ‫is super useful. Right? So you want to use it all the time. But in particular, right,
‫everyone tries to use radix ‫sort when it's inappropriate. ‫Right?
‫And they love, right, ‫because it gets linear time. ‫Right? ‫But ‫if you write
‫merge sort for something where radix sort will apply, you'll ‫get some points because it's correct but not efficient.
‫Right? ‫And ‫it's inefficient by ‫a log factor. Right?
‫If you're trying to use radix sort in a situation where comparisons ‫are the answer and you don't have a bound on the integers,
‫if I don't have a bound on the size of ‫the integers, then this may be taking a
‫huge amount of time. Right?
‫So I might not even think of that as being ‫correct because it could be exponential time. ‫Right?
‫I mean, I don't know. I don't know how big ‫my word size is. It could be arbitrarily bad. ‫OK?
‫And then if you're trying to augment a binary tree with something that's not a subtree ‫property, right, something that can't be computed from the augmentations of its two children,
‫you're doing something ‫bad. I mean, every exam, ‫we have ‫30 % of students say,
‫augment by my index ‫in the entire tree. ‫Right? ‫Or augment by, ‫here's one that's fun,
‫augment by the things the ‫size of my left subtree. ‫OK?
‫Like the number of ‫nodes in my left subtree.
‫I'm not sure how I can maintain that ‫with rotations and things like that. ‫Let's see.
‫In order for me to keep track of ‫the augmentation of my left tree
‫from the augmentation of my left tree, right, I kind of have to do a logarithmic ‫walk all the way down the thing to figure out how many things were there. Right?
‫So that's not a maintainable thing in constant time. If I want to augment something of my left ‫subtree, just augment the thing itself and just look at your left subtree and look at its augmentation.
‫Does that make sense?
‫Yeah? If you had, say, augmented it with a subtree and then augmented it again with left subtree and then used that. JASON KU - You could do ‫that. That's still kind of like .. JASON KU - You could do that. Yeah. So you could do that in constant time by augmenting by subtree size.
‫Right? Yeah, and then have another augmentation in the node thing. JASON KU - You could have another ‫augmentation because then you could just look at, but then just look at your left subtree, please.
‫Yeah?
‫No reason to store it again. Right? You just do one constant ‫time look to your left subtree. JASON KU - To your left, right?
‫OK. ‫Don't do that. ‫OK. ‫So that is cool. I'm ‫not that far behind.
‫Those are my tips ‫on solving questions. ‫Oh, there's one more, ‫Paige. Yeah?
‫So in defining an augmentation, you just have to give a formula and argue that it's random ‫constant time? JASON KU - Exactly, right? So the idea is if you give an augmentation that's
‫not stand, like
‫we're going to talk about our standard things you can reduce to in a second, if you're saying, I'm going to take a set AVL ‫tree or a sequence AVL tree, and like, for example, at the end of lecture, we were talking about how a sequence AVL tree
‫could
‫be modified to support priority queue operations ‫in the same running times as binary heaps.
‫And that was saying, ‫we store our subtree maxes, ‫the max thing in my subtree. ‫Right?
‫And so that's a different augmentation ‫than what's already augmented on ‫the sequence AVL tree.
‫What are the augmentations ‫on a sequence AVL tree? ‫Size. ‫Count.
‫JASON KU - So count is the same thing ‫as how many nodes are in my subtree. ‫And?
‫Height. JASON KU - Height, ‫right, because it's an AVL tree. ‫Right?
‫So if I'm augmenting ‫by max in my subtree, ‫that's not part of ‫my standard interface.
‫So you need to tell me that. Even though we've ‫done it before, it should be very easy for you.
‫Just say, I'm ‫augmenting by my max.
‫Max can be computed as the max between me ‫and my left and right subtree if they exist. ‫Done.
‫But just do that.
‫You have to tell me, and it takes constant time, so it can ‫be maintained in constant time when I'm doing my stuff.
‫Does that make sense? ‫OK. ‫So the last thing, I guess,
‫especially on the data ‫structures problems, ‫I would suggest
‫that you approach these things by solving these ‫problems just in terms of the interfaces first,
‫because then at least you ‫get something that's correct.
‫And then choose the algorithms or data structures ‫that you use to implement those interfaces afterwards.
‫One gets you to a correct ‫algorithm. The other is for efficiency.
‫So that's going to help ‫you in solving the problem. ‫If it doesn't help you, don't.
‫If you're like, whenever I see a set data structure, I'm ‫going to probably use a hash table, that's probably fine.
‫But if we're looking for worst case ‫time bounds, that's probably not fine.
‫So just you, I'm suggesting
‫that you separate these things so that you concentrate ‫on solving the problem first and then optimize it later.
‫Yeah? ‫Just a question in regards ‫to worst case time bounds.
‫So for a hash table, even ‫though that's all one expected,
‫that also implies that's all n worst case. So could you ‫technically? JASON KU - It doesn't imply that. It is that.
‫So I mean, you could have a data structure whose expected ‫time bound is constant, but its worst case bound is n log n.
‫It just happens to be the fact that for a hash ‫table, those worst case operations are linear.
‫But if I had, we had ‫a question up here.
‫Beforehand, if I had a running time bound that I did something ‫to a hash table in constant expected time, I did a look up.
‫And then I queried an AVL tree for the ‫predecessor of a node or something like that.
‫And I did that in ‫o of log n time.
‫What's the worst case running time ‫of that? O of n. JASON KU - o of n.
‫What's the expected ‫running time of this thing? ‫o of n. JASON KU - log n.
‫Expected log n. Because it's possible ‫that in the worst case, it could be higher.
‫Does that make sense? ‫OK. ‫So OK, the second bullet is
‫just setting up a data structures ‫problem. There's a lot of moving parts.
‫We're going to do two data structures ‫problem at the end of this session.
‫Describe all of the data ‫structures you're using.
‫JASON KU - Including what they store. If you're storing a set ‫data structure, you better tell me what the things you're stored
‫are keyed on. ‫Usually, the things that we're ‫storing contain a bunch of information.
‫And if you just say, I'm storing all of the ‫toppings of my pizza in a set data structure,
‫and that's all you tell me, I have no idea what you're talking about. Because I ‫don't know what the semantics of your set data structure are. What is it keyed on?
‫I have to say, ‫oh, it's keyed on, ‫I don't know, the y's. ‫Or something like that.
‫And they're invariants.
‫How we're setting up these data structures problem, ‫usually how I solve these when I'm writing the solutions,
‫I set you up a state of what this ‫data structure could be at some instance. ‫I'm going to say,
‫this data structure stores ‫all of the things less than k
‫with key less than ‫k, blah, blah, blah. ‫And this one stores the ‫extrinsic order of
‫the items based on ‫blah, blah, blah.
‫So actually, me stating what they store in that way is actually imposing ‫some kind of invariant on these data structures that I'm wanting to maintain.
‫But what I need to do to prove ‫that this thing is correct is that,
‫based on the assumption ‫that those invariants held ‫before my operation,
‫then I can prove that an ‫operation is correct if all of those
‫invariants are maintained ‫before then after the operation.
‫That's how I'm proving ‫that this thing is correct.
‫And then when I'm querying, I'm doing some ‫kind of look up on this data structure.
‫I can rely on those invariants. ‫I know that those ‫things are good. ‫Those things
‫have been maintained. And so I can rely on those to look up ‫what's the largest k of this thing. Does that kind of make sense?
‫This is very abstract. We're ‫going to get a little bit more ‫concrete in just a second.
‫And then implement every operation. You have no ‫idea how many solutions we read on the quizzes,
‫which we give you ‫three operations to implement, ‫and you don't even mention one.
‫And it's usually ‫the easiest one. ‫It's like, insert it ‫into your data structure.
‫It's like, come on, just say that. We can't give ‫you points unless you mention that operation.
‫Does that make sense? ‫And then it's going ‫to help us read. ‫Happy graders give ‫you more points.
‫Not really, ‫but if your solution is well -organized ‫and well -labeled and things like that,
‫then we're going to be able to comprehend your solution ‫better, and we'll be able to give you more points.
‫Remember, part of this ‫class is about communication. ‫If your thing is correct,
‫but we can't tell ‫what you're saying, ‫then it's not correct.
‫So now we get to any ‫questions on that? ‫Yeah. Just a question ‫about the invariants.
‫So for the data structures that we've discussed in the past, are you ‫still going to say what the invariants are, like the set ABL3 will?
‫JASON KUO - Right. So if it's the standard things, we're ‫going to talk about what the standard things are now.
‫Then you don't need to re -argue or restate ‫all of that. I mean, you can basically say,
‫because the set and sequence interfaces are ‫defined that way, these things are correct. ‫You're
‫trying to convince us that ‫you know why it's correct.
‫If you're correctly using a set or a sequence data ‫structure in these data structures -type problems,
‫then unless you're using ‫it in a way that is unusual,
‫usually you can just rely on the properties of the ‫set and sequence data structures that we gave you.
‫I do want you to mention that ‫you thought about correctness, ‫like
‫this data structure ‫is correct because. ‫Just write a sentence ‫saying that and
‫arguing that you're
‫basically maintaining the invariants of your ‫data structure, kind of at the upper level.
‫What kinds of things is ‫this data structure storing?
‫What things about the ‫global data structure
‫are we relying on to make query operations? As long as you are convincing that after a dynamic operation ‫where I'm modifying the data structure, that those invariants stay the same, that are still satisfied,
‫then that's really ‫all you need to say.
‫These invariants are satisfied because of the definitions of the set and sequence ‫data structure. Like, a lot of times, it doesn't require a lot of thought.
‫We're not asking. ‫The reason why we ‫do reduction problems
‫is so that you don't have to do a lot ‫of work to prove to us that it's correct.
‫We have these really ‫nice black boxes. ‫They are correct.
‫We proved them to you ‫that they're correct. ‫And so you don't have ‫to redo that work.
‫So now we're going to go through the core ‫material I like to think about in this class.
‫The first part of this class, aside from these mathematical tools that we developed at ‫the beginning of the course, it's mostly about solving problems involving data structures.
‫And we motivated this problem of sorting by saying that a ‫sorted array is a data structure that's actually pretty useful.
‫But how do we sort those things? ‫Well, we showed you a ‫bunch of ways to do that.
‫And this is that nice table, ‫lots of stuff.
‫Why do we show you so many sorting algorithms? ‫Why don't we just give you one algorithm? ‫Hm?
‫Yeah? ‫Different run times.
‫Better for different scenarios. Better for different scenarios. ‫Yeah, they each have their own individual points that may be better.
‫But in this table, ‫there's not blue all the way ‫across for any of these things.
‫So some of them are better ‫for different scenarios. ‫And actually, ‫these comments list
‫some special cases where ‫these things might be better.
‫In actuality, this ultra blue thing ‫is saying this could be linear time. ‫That's better.
‫But in some cases, this is ‫worse than all the other things.
‫Be a little wary of ‫this blue color here.
‫Generally, we're trying to get you down ‫further down in this chart if you can. ‫And in general,
‫for example, merge ‫sort, AVL sort, ‫these are really
‫the same in terms of asymptotic complexity and the way ‫in which you interact with these sorting algorithms.
‫But there are special ‫cases where you might
‫use insertion sort or selection sort. ‫Actually, I'm not sure about insertion sort.
‫You had a in your recitation ‫two days ago, ‫I think you guys ‫showed how to
‫do if you had a k -proximate array where things ‫are not more than k away from each other.
‫Insertion sort actually runs in n times k. ‫And so if k is small, then that's really good.
‫That's kind of like linear. ‫But you can actually ‫do even better
‫with a binary heap, which you saw in your recitation, ‫hopefully, where you can get that down to n log k
‫by maintaining a heap as you go ‫across and finding the max that way.
‫So insertion sort ‫maybe is not so great. ‫But selection sort, the ‫name of the game there is that
‫if ‫my reads are cheap but ‫my writes are expensive,
‫selection sort actually does pretty ‫well because I only have to do, sorry,
‫my reads are cheap and ‫my writes are expensive.
‫Selection sort only does ‫a linear number of swaps.
‫It's looking down, finding the ‫max, swapping it in, and keep going.
‫And so in such cases, ‫that's actually better than ‫any of these other ‫algorithms that we've got.
‫Yeah? ‫Is heap sort time ‫worst case or expected? ‫JASON KUO - This is worst case.
‫So it's a little hard to put. There ‫was a lot of moving parts to get to this
‫bound in Tuesday's lecture. ‫But basically what we ‫did, we showed you how
‫to think of an array as a heap, ‫as a binary tree, ‫complete binary tree.
‫It's not an AVL. I ‫mean, it is an AVL tree. ‫But AVL trees are weaker ‫than a complete tree.
‫Height balance is a weaker ‫property than a complete. ‫The reason why we ‫use complete is because
‫it's unique ‫for a number of nodes.
‫That way, when I give you one array with a fixed length, I know exactly ‫what tree you're talking about because there's a one -to -one mapping there.
‫If ‫there was some ambiguity on ‫what tree I was talking about, ‫heaps just wouldn't work.
‫So what heap sort does is it has this ‫correspondence between arrays and binary trees.
‫And then what it does is provides these ‫operations that only do operations at the end.
‫And then the in -place optimization is that, well, instead of actually popping it or pushing ‫it onto the back of an array, I'm just going to think of a subset of my array as a heap
‫and then always kind ‫of pooping the ‫max out to the end,
‫just leaving it behind and thinking ‫of my heap as a smaller subset. ‫And that's how we got it.
‫It didn't actually ‫use any amortization. ‫So for the time bound,
‫time bound, you could actually do this with ‫the amortized, basically, dynamic array
‫version of this. The time ‫bound doesn't rely on that.
‫The in -place relies on staying all ‫within one array. Does that make sense?
‫You're doing a bunch of amortized operations so that ‫this actually does achieve worst case NLogN. Yeah?
‫It seems that the things we learn do not like ‫such a long time ago. Or they tend to be better.
‫I assume that most algorithms, ‫we want them to be faster.
‫It seems like we will not use as often, especially ‫in the exam, as well, insertion and selection.
‫JASON KUO - Right, yeah. So there are ‫these special cases where they're good.
‫But generally, these are better general data ‫structures for most situations that you come across.
‫There are cases where those other things are ‫good, so you don't want to completely ignore them.
‫But generally,
‫yeah. JASON KUO - You're trying to be lower down in this chart. What I mean is that ‫if I don't have an exam, I'm using them all, except for selection .. JASON KUO - So
‫there's too many things on here ‫for us to test all of them on an exam.
‫So don't be afraid if ‫not everything is covered.
‫Worry when things are covered 18 ‫times on the exam. That's not good. ‫So for radix sort,
‫there are situations where you get linear ‫time. It's when you're polynomially bounded. ‫I want to
‫use radix sort when I'm not ‫polynomially bounded in my integers.
‫Well, if you're not ‫polynomially bounded, ‫then that could take ‫a really long time.
‫JASON KUO - Sure, ‫yeah. ‫But where is the, ‫this will be worse ‫than n log n when?
‫It's definitely better than n log n ‫when u is polynomially bounded. Right? ‫Because it's linear.
‫Yeah? ‫When is n to the n? ‫JASON KUO - n to the n.
‫OK, so if I put n to ‫the n in here, I get an n ‫factor that comes out here.
‫That gives me a ‫quadratic running time, ‫which is not great.
‫But when will this ‫be better than n log n? ‫Yeah? ‫n to the c u is ‫less than n to the c.
‫JASON KUO - n to the c. So that'll definitely ‫give us linear time. That's what this is saying.
‫But we can actually ‫do better than n log n ‫if ‫this u is n to ‫the c times log n for some c.
‫If it's asymptotic, like ‫if it's n to the c log log n,
‫that's smaller than log n. ‫So that's a better algorithm. ‫That's a faster algorithm.
‫Do you guys see why we wrote these things? JASON KUO - Yeah. We wrote ‫these things this way is so that we give you a more precise about.
‫This is more important for you to understand what u means ‫here than that this thing sometimes runs in linear time.
‫We want to know when ‫it runs in linear time. ‫Does that make sense?
‫Or when it runs ‫faster than merge sort. ‫Does that make sense? ‫OK, so that's sorting.
‫We have sequence ‫type data structures. ‫We have linked lists.
‫We have dynamic arrays. ‫We have sequence ABLs. ‫Sequence ABLs are great.
‫I don't know why no one ‫teaches it. They're great.
‫They don't teach it probably because ‫they're actually not that useful.
‫You don't actually use ‫the insert in the middle a ‫lot in coding.
‫So you can usually get around with shifting something to the end and doing dynamic operations there. ‫And that's a lot of the games that you try to play. So you don't have to make your own data structure.
‫There's and you can ‫just use the Python list ‫that's native to your thing.
‫But it has a theoretical interest because it gets these kind ‫of bounds if you need to insert in the middle of this sequence.
‫Now, some of you look at me and ‫had a question before that was like, ‫but Jason, ‫how
‫does linked list ‫operations on the end ‫of a linked list, why ‫does that take linear time?
‫It's because in lecture, ‫we presented you with what? ‫A singly linked list.
‫It just had pointers ‫to the next thing.
‫And if I only have pointers to the ‫next thing and a pointer to the head, ‫for me to find the end,
‫I need to walk all ‫the way down the list. ‫Now, let's say I keep ‫my pointer to the tail.
‫Doing that end one is fine.
‫But removing it still takes linear time ‫because I don't know what came before me.
‫And so that's why in pset whatever, 1, 2, I don't remember, you stored ‫a pointer back to your previous one that gave you doubly linked lists.
‫Yay. ‫So actually, expanding ‫this table out,
‫you can reference a doubly linked list ‫here and get this one as constant time.
‫Does that make sense? ‫JASON KU - Yeah, but this ‫one's still linear time.
‫But this one's ‫still linear time.
‫We actually also showed you how ‫to do this in constant amortized. ‫Do you guys remember that?
‫That was in problem session ‫2 or 1. I don't remember.
‫It was whatever we were ‫talking about amortized stuff.
‫We got actually both of these to 1 amortized ‫using the concepts of the dynamic array.
‫And then we actually did it one more time ‫where we got a good doubly ended thing. ‫What was that?
‫Does anyone remember? ‫We went ‫to problem session 3. ‫Yeah? Oh, I'm probably wrong.
‫This is not from problem session 3. But like QDQ, that stuff? ‫JASON KU - So QDQ, those are talking about doubly ended things.
‫Those are implemented in a certain way, which is actually ‫one of these things. It's actually, I think, this one
‫in pi. ‫But we used a different data structure ‫to get something that had really good at.
‫It had really ‫good pop and append ‫first and last ‫dynamic operations.
‫Do you guys remember ‫problem session 3? ‫JASON KU - ‫That's what this was. ‫We
‫got one that had ‫expected bounds. ‫Does that help? ‫I heard someone say it. ‫Hash table. ‫Yeah.
‫So what basically you did, ‫instead of, ‫this is a sequence thing. ‫These things don't have keys.
‫But ‫I could identify with each item as I ‫stick it in a key representing its index.
‫And I could use a hash ‫table that way. Now, there was
‫some difficulty if I ‫removed the first thing. ‫JASON KU - Yeah. ‫Right? ‫Because actually,
‫all of my indices ‫have now changed. ‫But if I just store what the ‫smallest index in my thing is,
‫then ‫I'm golden because I can compute what that ‫index should be as I change things at the front.
‫OK, so there's actually three different ways we showed you of ‫getting constant time at the front and the back of this thing.
‫So actually, you can think of that as ‫standard material that you can reduce to. ‫OK?
‫That's the one exception of the things ‫that I'm not showing on this chart,
‫but is a bonus if you're watching this problem session. Yeah? So ‫isn't a hash table a set data structure, though? JASON KU - It is.
‫Right? But we used it to ‫implement a sequence data structure.
‫So I will refer you to that problem ‫session if you want to learn more about it. ‫OK?
‫So any questions on sequence ‫data structures? Yeah?
‫A different question. ‫JASON KU - Yeah. Uh -huh? ‫Should we be able to prove
‫the tables that were given? ‫JASON KU - So I would hope, ‫I hope,
‫that if I gave ‫you a blank table, ‫that you would be ‫able to fill it out.
‫Right? That's how well I want you to ‫know how these things are implemented.
‫We're not going to ‫have that on the exam. ‫Right? ‫That's a boring ‫kind of question.
‫But it is important to know. ‫JASON KU - Yeah. ‫I would,
‫you know, it's good for you to think, like, oh, if I'm going to use ‫an AVL tree, right, operations are generally going to be log in.
‫Right? That's a really useful thing. Or ‫if I'm going to use a hash table, right,
‫dictionary type operations, you know, finding, ‫inserting, and deleting, those are fast.
‫Doing order type operations on hash tables is bad. That's hard ‫to do, because I have to basically look through all my things.
‫Right? ‫Knowing that dynamic operations ‫on assorted array is bad. ‫Right?
‫Or knowing that, you know,
‫you have to think about here what we mean when we ‫say, linked list and dynamic array in this table.
‫Right?
‫Because you've - Yeah, exactly. We are implying singly linked ‫here, because that's what we presented to you in lecture.
‫And so those are the standard things that we want you to reduce to. So the three modified standard things are the double -ended list, the double ‫-ended dynamic array? JASON KU - Yeah. Basically, you can assume that you have a double - It's this one that you probably want to use. Right? Because
‫you get constant indexing. ‫Right? ‫And then pretty good ‫on both ends. Right? But,
‫you know, if you need a double -ended queue, you can also reduce it to having ‫two dynamic arrays back to back, one going this way, one going this way.
‫And so there's lots of way - We're not going to give that to you as a standard ‫method, because there's literally like four methods we showed you how to do.
‫Right? So you choose one. ‫Okay? Yeah?
‫In the interest of saving time on the example, like if we want to say, like, we do this thing with the sequence ‫A, B, I, I, and it takes long end time, like do we have to say the sentence, like, because it's a sequence A, B,
‫L, it takes long end time? Because this - Or can we just, like, say, like, per the table that we ‫know? JASON KU - Yeah. No. If you told me that you're storing things in a sequence A, B, I, right?
‫And you just say - You basically say what you do to it, and you say which takes blah, blah, blah ‫time, you don't need to say because it's a sequence A, B, I, right? Because you already told us it's a
‫sequence A, B, L. I believe that you probably wrote ‫the chart on your cheat sheet and you looked it up.
‫Okay? ‫All right. ‫Any other questions on this? ‫No? ‫Yeah.
‫Just to make sure, the double -linked list will make the insert, ‫last, and the delete box be all one. Is that the only change?
‫JASON KU - Yes. ‫A double -linked list ‫gives this guy constant time.
‫And actually, there are two operations here, insert, ‫delete, and I guess there's a find here as well, right?
‫If I just store the tail pointer, that ‫gets the find to constant time, right?
‫But it doesn't get the dynamic ones to constant time, right? I need to ‫store the previous pointers as well. So I'm going to do that with each node.
‫Does that make sense? ‫Okay. ‫Lastly, ‫or I guess second to ‫lastly, set data structures.
‫There are a little ‫bit more of these, ‫not so many more. ‫But yeah,
‫we had a sorted array, gets good ‫find, but is not dynamic, right? ‫We have set AVL tree,
‫which does pretty good ‫find and is dynamic. Again, ‫you get this n log n
‫overhead to build because essentially what you're doing ‫with both of those data structures is to sort, right?
‫But if I'm looking ‫on a theory question, ‫right,
‫like I'm not asking you something ‫specifically about a sorted array,
‫right, if you have a choice between this data structure ‫and this data structure, which one do you choose?
‫Well, I don't quite know.
‫Because it's almost like this one's better ‫at everything except for this one, right?
‫But can anyone tell me how to ‫make this one constant time as well?
‫Augmentation, right? I could just store ‫in my subtrees the max or min, right?
‫And I can make this one strictly better than this one, right? So ‫in a theory problem, you probably just want to use this one, right?
‫Here, hash tables, ‫direct access arrays, ‫even better for ‫these operations. ‫Right?
‫But they suck at these, ‫right? So if you need ‫these, don't use these, right?
‫And in actual coding, right, especially if you're coding in a language that's not Python, something that doesn't automatically give you a hash table, ‫right? If you're in C, in a microcontroller lab at MIT here, you're taking 6, 1, 15 or whatever, right? Like, and you're doing assembly, right?
‫Usually what you're doing ‫is a direct access stuff, ‫right?
‫Because that's giving you the jumps that you need in machine learning. In machine language to ‫actually go and access this constant time, that's general. If you have control over the keys that
‫you're putting in your data ‫structure, you don't want
‫this overhead of running your keys through ‫a hash function to look these things up.
‫You just store the ‫things in array, right? ‫You use the hash table when
‫you don't have control over the keys or your ‫keys are like strings or something, right?
‫So that's when you ‫use the hash table. ‫Now, for our purposes, usually,
‫you know, a hash table is just as good unless ‫we're asking you for worst case bounds, ‫right?
‫And if we,
‫we're going to do this when we talk about the data ‫structures problem. If we give you a situation
‫where we don't care
‫if you achieve worst case or expected or amortized or any of these ‫things, we'll just say, make sure you state which one you achieve,
‫right?
‫And as long as you analyzed it correctly with ‫respect to your data structures, then you're fine,
‫right? But if we say you ‫better do worst case, here, ‫I'm going to slap you around, ‫right? ‫Then
‫please get those bounds, right? ‫Don't use the hash table in that case. ‫Does that make sense?
‫OK. ‫Lastly, we've got priority ‫queues, which we talked about.
‫I'm not going to go through this one ‫very much. It's basically just adding this ‫to the thing.
‫But in actuality, you can ‫get all of these bounds with
‫a set AVL, I mean, a ‫sequence AVL tree with ‫max or min augmentation,
‫which isn't on this list because we didn't ‫really talk about it. But hopefully, you can.
‫If you need these bounds ‫without the amortization, ‫then you could achieve them, OK?
‫All right, so that's basically everything ‫that we've talked about in the class, OK?
‫We're going to spend the rest of the time ‫working a couple data structures problem.
‫There's a number of different ‫types of questions you'll actually see
‫in the quiz, the practice quiz ‫that we gave you from last term.
‫There's some what I call mechanical ‫type questions up at the front, ‫right?
‫Then usually some reduction type problems where you're reducing ‫to using some sorting algorithms or some data structures.
‫And then usually the latter ones are ones where you have to do ‫some kind of something additional, like some augmentation or
‫some divide and conquer or ‫something like that, right? ‫OK,
‫so we're going to go ahead and spend the rest ‫of the time working a couple of these problems.
‫These were from spring ‫of 2019 on the exam. ‫And actually,
‫one of the TAs who's TAing for us now was also TAing for us in spring 19, was grading problem ‫number two here, the rainy research problem, and just hated me because no one did it right.
‫So all right, ‫so let's try to solve ‫these problems. Problem one ‫is about restaurant.
‫Stor -rant, yes, OK. ‫All right, so basically ‫what's happening?
‫Popular restaurant, ‫criminal seafood. ‫What's the reference? ‫Legal.
‫Does not take reservations, but maintains a wait list where ‫customers who have been on the wait list longer are seated earlier.
‫Sometimes customers decide to eat somewhere else, so ‫the restaurant must remove them from the wait list. OK,
‫assume that a customer has a different name. No two customers are added to the wait list at the exact same time, ‫right? So there's kind of an ordering at which people are being added to this wait list, right? Does that make sense?
‫Design a database to help criminal seafood maintain its wait ‫lists, supporting the following operations, each in constant time.
‫OK, so here we've refactored ‫the running time up to the top.
‫And it's, oh, sorry, ‫I added the build here.
‫I guess that's still ‫constant time. That's fine, OK.
‫Yeah, state whether each running ‫time operation is, worst case,
‫amortized, expested. So when you see that statement, you're ‫saying, OK, I'm allowed to use a hash table if I want to.
‫I just have to make sure if I use one, I ‫label my operations expected and amortized
‫when they occur. ‫Which ‫operations are expected? ‫Basically all of them.
‫Which operations are amortized? The ones that ‫changed what's in the data structure, right?
‫Insert, delete. ‫OK, so we've got some operations, ‫building an empty thing,
‫adding a name, so this name is ‫x, to the back of the wait list. ‫What do I know about x?
‫What do I know about the names ‫per our assumptions ‫in this class?
‫They're all unique, so they can be a key. JASON ‫KUO - They're unique, so they can be a key. And
‫they fit in a constant number of words by our assumption, right? So I can ‫compare two of them in constant, or I can hash one in constant time, right?
‫That's kind of the assumption we ‫make on these inputs. They're strings.
‫And I didn't assign you a bound on their length, so it's ‫probably not something you need to worry about, right?
‫OK, ‫remove a name, right?
‫So already, I'm feeling like I need to be ‫able to find things by their name, right? ‫OK,
‫and then seat the ‫next person in line. ‫Does that make sense?
‫So what kinds of things ‫do I need to maintain here? ‫I have people, ‫right? They have names.
‫They have places, ‫the time that they ‫came in, right? ‫But am I given the times? ‫No.
‫I'm not given times anywhere, right? ‫It's not on the inputs to my operations,
‫right? So it's not like I'm ‫going to be able to key on times. ‫Does that make sense?
‫What's the important ‫part about times? ‫The order.
‫JASON KUO - The order, right? And you're ‫given that. JASON KUO - Yeah, basically,
‫whenever I'm basically trying to ‫maintain a sequence on these guys, right?
‫There's a front ‫one and a back one. ‫JASON KUO - And ‫people in the middle,
‫right? And I want to make sure that order stays the same or else people are going to get angry at ‫me, right? Because, ah, they came here after me and ready to go to the city for it. Yeah, right?
‫You've been in that situation.
‫OK, so we're trying to maintain some kind of ‫sequence, an extrinsic order on these things,
‫right?
‫But we're also needing to be able to look up people by their ‫name because I want to be able to change this thing, right?
‫Does this maybe sound familiar to ‫some other problem we had on this? ‫This term's problem sets?
‫Yeah, I think there was ‫a problem where the chat, ‫right? You had to ‫store a sequence, right?
‫But you also had this dictionary ‫that you had to look things up, right?
‫Now, the nice thing about that ‫situation is that the things ‫that you needed to look up on
‫was static, ‫right? ‫And so what could I use for my ‫dictionary, my set data structure for that?
‫JASON KUO - Anyone remember?
‫You could just use a sorted array, right? Because it's static, these things aren't ‫updating all the time, right? And so it was fine for me to just use a static array, right?
‫Here, ‫and we gave you look up times that ‫were worst case logarithmic, right?
‫Here, I'm asking for ‫constant time, right? ‫Sorted array is ‫not going to cut it.
‫Set AVL is not going to cut ‫it. So what am I going to use? ‫A
‫dynamic array or a ‫hash table. Right?
‫Now, dynamic array might not be great because I don't actually have a ‫numeric bound on how big these keys are. I just know that they fit in words,
‫right?
‫So I can't actually make a direct access array because those words, while they fit in a constant ‫number of words, I don't know if the integer representation of those are polynomially bounded.
‫Does that make sense?
‫Right? So I do want to use hashing in this case, right? ‫And so what do I want to maintain? I want to maintain
‫a sequence data structure. ‫On customers. ‫Customers.
‫Is there a U in there somewhere? ‫No, this is right, right? ‫OK, and a set mapping.
‫So this is usually how I do it. I ‫want to say a set keyed on something.
‫If it's just a set, then I just have it keyed, right? ‫I can look up whether that thing is there or not.
‫But when I'm actually having it mapped to something else, I'll say mapping a key space to something else, usually ‫the item that I'm storing or maybe some property of the items that I'm storing. Right? Does that make sense?
‫OK, so mapping, ‫what do I map here? ‫Names, ‫right? ‫To. ‫Oh, to what? Do I want to map?
‫The time. ‫The time that they entered. ‫Do I want to do that? ‫Well,
‫we can't exactly do it with the time that they entered, but the sequence and the customers will show ‫what's next and what's not. Yeah, kind of I want to store it to where it is in this sequence, right?
‫So I'll just store the index where it is in the ‫sequence, and I can just look it up, right? That sounds.
‫Yeah? ‫Is
‫that what? Well, I couldn't indices change. Yeah, indices ‫change every time I add or remove things, right? Ah, yeah.
‫Store a pointer. Right? ‫Pointer to place ‫in sequence. ‫Now,
‫that's a little weird to say because I haven't ‫told you how I represented this sequence, ‫right?
‫But conceptually, I can say I'm storing a pointer to some place in this ‫that represents where it is. I'll deal with the details of that later, OK?
‫Right?
‫But generally, I call this a linked data structure, ‫right? Because I'm linking between two data structures,
‫right? ‫So that I can do a query in one, say, and ‫find out where it is in the other, right?
‫Or do a query in the other, ‫that kind of thing, OK?
‫So everyone kind of understand ‫why I chose these things,
‫right? How I approach ‫this problem? Yeah?
‫I'm not sure how a pointer fixes ‫a problem of just storing an index.
‫But I'm just wondering if the place that the person is at in the sequence is going ‫to change over time. Or are you assuming that the pointer updates with that change?
‫So OK. ‫So let's say if ‫every time, so let's say I'm ‫storing this sequence in a linked list.
‫Let's just say.
‫Because I know that I'm going to have to be inserting ‫and deleting things from the middle of this thing.
‫Does that make sense? ‫Yeah. All right.
‫So I'm going to go ahead and say ‫that this is going to be a linked list, ‫OK? ‫This linked list,
‫OK? ‫So if ‫I said,
‫all right, this set data structure, my set, stores ‫pointer or stores where it is in the linked list,
‫right? Say it's stored at k, ‫right? Cool. ‫Now, if ‫I see it's this guy, ‫right? ‫At his table,
‫right? ‫Every index has changed, right?
‫So for me to update the indexes stored in this set data ‫structure, I have to change every single one of them.
‫Yeah. Does that make sense? ‫Yeah. No, this ‫makes way more sense.
‫Yeah. So really what I want, not to store a number here, but ‫an actual pointer to the node that's containing this thing,
‫right? Because the node isn't changing unless ‫that thing left my data structure, right?
‫The node, the address ‫of this thing in memory,
‫the node is just a little container that contains an item and the next ‫pointer. And actually, we're going to need a previous pointer here,
‫right? We're going to ‫need a double linked list,
‫right? Because what we're going to do when we ‫remove something, we need to stitch it back together
‫in constant time, which means we need to know what's ‫the one in front of us and the one behind us, right?
‫Yeah? ‫All right. So linked list here, ‫we already said maybe ‫using a hash table here. ‫Right?
‫And so, OK, great. ‫This is basically ‫enough for me to say, ‫this is my data structure.
‫These are the invariants. ‫What are the invariants? ‫It's storing all the customers, ‫right?
‫That's an invariant. ‫I mean, it's not a ‫very strong invariant,
‫but it's, I mean, I should say that, right? I'm storing all the customers because ‫I'm going to have to make sure that I'm maintaining that when I do a query, right?
‫And then here, set mapping ‫names to pointers, right? ‫The place in this thing, right?
‫And as I remove things, I need to make ‫sure that invariant stays the same, right?
‫It's still mapping all the names ‫of customers that I have in my thing ‫to their nodes, ‫OK?
‫So when something leaves, I better need ‫to make sure that both of these things ‫are updated.
‫Does that make sense? ‫OK. So how do I maintain ‫these operations? We've got ‫a build.
‫Build just sets up empty ‫of these things, right? ‫So you just say that.
‫I build an empty linked list, doubly linked ‫list on the customers, and I build a set,
‫a hash table mapping nothing ‫to nothing right now, right? ‫OK. ‫So that's build.
‫I'm going to be precise here and actually write ‫down the thing because I told you not to ignore
‫a operation or else we ‫can't give you points for it. ‫The next one, yeah?
‫By building an empty linked list, you mean like it just has ‫like the head and the tail are set to none, but like it exists?
‫Yeah, right. It's a thing ‫in memory that we store.
‫It has a pointer to a head and ‫a tail. Those are none right now,
‫but we will add things ‫to it, right? OK. ‫So the second one, ‫add name, right?
‫What do we have to say?
‫We have to update this data structure ‫so it maintains it to variance, right?
‫I have to, usually I ‫start with one of them. ‫I get to a point where,
‫oh, I really should have ‫updated the other one first, ‫right? ‫So sometimes it's hit or miss.
‫What do I want to do here? Well, I have ‫no idea where in this sequence this is, ‫right?
‫So I kind of have ‫to go here first, ‫right? ‫Oh, sorry. ‫Adding a guy,
‫I kind of have to go here first. ‫I could do either way, right? ‫I know where is he going to go?
‫End of the list, right? ‫So I can just stick ‫it there, right? ‫So add x to end of sequence.
‫All right, so ‫I've already come to a ‫trick that I like, right? ‫Sequence, set.
‫OK, in this instance, I only have one sequence and one set. ‫And so calling them sequence and set is probably fine. Right?
‫I'm not going to confuse the grader. ‫I'm not going to confuse myself, right?
‫But when I have more than one of these things, or even ‫for brevity on an exam where I'm time constrained,
‫give these things a name, ‫right? ‫Say this is a sequence ‫C and M. I don't know.
‫I see customer ‫here. I see map here. ‫So maybe. I don't know, right?
‫But just give them a letter, and we can follow you much more clearly, ‫and you can refer to these things more precisely, right, so end of C.
‫OK? ‫Then what do we have to do? ‫I fix this guy. ‫This guy is good. ‫Now I have to fix this guy.
‫So I add x to the set,
‫and I map it back to that node that I just came from, ‫right? I could store it in a temporary variable, right?
‫Add x ‫to M pointing to ‫in ‫node v to v. ‫OK, cool?
‫So I added my x to the ‫end of C into a node v, ‫right?
‫I labeled it so I can ‫reference it later, right?
‫And kind of in code, I would ‫probably remember what that node was.
‫Add x to M pointing ‫to that node, ‫right? And now I've ‫maintained my invariant. ‫Great.
‫Maybe what's this? ‫Add ‫key x,
‫or add x to M having the key of x ‫point to that node. Does that make sense?
‫There's a little subtlety there. ‫OK? ‫3, ‫we have remove. ‫I don't remember ‫the name, whatever.
‫OK? ‫So here, we have to do the order matters, ‫right? I don't know where it is in the sequence.
‫But I'm going to ‫look it up in the set. ‫I'm going to remove ‫it from the set.
‫And I'm going to look at whatever it ‫points to and remove it from the sequence. ‫OK?
‫I'm running out of time a little bit here, so I'm not going to ‫write all that down. But you guys understand what that means.
‫Here, we're using the fact ‫that it's a doubly linked list
‫so that we can relink things ‫together. You don't have to tell me,
‫repoint the previous pointer ‫of my next thing to the next, ‫right?
‫You don't have to tell me how to relink those ‫pointers because we did that already in problem set
‫one or whatever, right?
‫Just in general, is there any situation for where using not a doubly linked list would be like just the ‫linked list would be better than a doubly linked list? Because it seems like it always solves problems.
‫Yeah, doubly linked list is almost always strictly ‫better than a singly linked list in theory problems.
‫So yeah, use it. ‫OK. ‫And then seat, last one. ‫That's just ‫take the front of the sequence,
‫remove it, ‫change the head around. But I get ‫that you can delete first, right?
‫Reducing to the interface that we had. ‫You're deleting first on this sequence. ‫OK?
‫But now, we have a situation. I deleted the ‫first guy. How do I know who the first guy is?
‫Well, I'm storing its ‫name in there, right? ‫I'm storing the names ‫of these customers.
‫So I know who was at the front. ‫I look in this ‫set data structure, ‫and I remove that entry.
‫Does that make sense? ‫Because now, I no longer ‫need to maintain where he goes.
‫Now, in actuality, ‫I could just ‫not update this ‫set data structure.
‫But if I do that, then, well, my ‫running times are still linear time, right?
‫I'm not giving you ‫a bound on space. ‫I'm still constant time. ‫Sorry.
‫So you don't actually ‫have to do that removal. ‫But
‫if that customer comes back and ‫wants to get on the wait list again,
‫there are things ‫to consider, right? ‫OK. ‫So that's that question. ‫Next question, ‫last
‫10 minutes or so. ‫Rainy research. ‫This was a problem that ‫people had nightmares about. ‫OK.
‫So basically, we've ‫got Mether Wann. ‫He's a weatherman,
‫a scientist who ‫studies global rainfall. ‫And he's got a bunch ‫of sensors everywhere.
‫And each one can post to the cloud or something. A ‫measurement that's of the form a triple of integers, R,
‫L, and T, where R is a positive ‫amount of rainfall, an integer, ‫a latitude,
‫an integer again, and at a time. ‫OK. ‫So we've got three ‫things to deal with here. ‫Yuck. ‫OK.
‫But they're all integers. And ‫don't be like, oh, well, Jason, ‫latitudes are pretty small.
‫So I can assume these ‫integers are small.
‫They're constant time, right? I'm not specifying to ‫you a resolution at which I'm measuring these integers.
‫And I haven't given you a bound between what that resolution ‫is compared to the number of measurements that I have.
‫So don't play those games. ‫OK. ‫The peak rainfall at a given ‫latitude since a particular time
‫is the maximum rainfall at ‫any measurement at that latitude
‫measured at a time greater ‫than or equal to that time. ‫Does that make sense?
‫Or 0 if there aren't ‫measurements at that latitude. OK.
‫Or after the time, or ‫before the time, or whatever.
‫Describe a database that we ‫can build it in constant time, ‫right?
‫An empty one. I added this one because ‫we weren't good about that last spring.
‫Record data. We ‫give you a triplet. ‫And then, so record ‫data, for it to be correct,
‫I just have to maintain ‫that information, right? ‫For these kind of updates, ‫I don't,
‫it's really hard for me to ‫argue that this thing is correct, ‫right?
‫Because I just, you know, I throw it at the database. The ‫database doesn't have to give anything back to me, right?
‫So
‫the important thing here about correctness is that peak rainfall gives it to me, and it gives it to me in the time ‫bound that I'm looking for. And peak rainfall is returning the peak rainfall at a particular latitude since t.
‫OK. ‫So we have three things. ‫Yep.
‫Measurement is like a technique that we just have a record of it. There's the potential that you don't need to store all of the information ‫because all we're doing is giving you back r's, essentially, right? It's possible that you don't need to store the latitudes or times at all,
‫right? You don't even ‫need to store the triplets.
‫Now, in reality, I'm querying ‫on the latitudes and the times.
‫So I should store them somewhere, but I might ‫be able to compress them. In particular, ‫right?
‫Many things could be ‫stored at the same latitude, ‫right?
‫That's kind of the ‫whole point of the query. ‫And so we want,
‫I mean, we may only need to store ‫that latitude once. Does that make sense?
‫OK. I'm going to wait for questions and laughter ‫because I want to get to a solution to this problem.
‫All right.
‫So what do we need to do? We need to be able to add things, and I ‫want to return. So return, I'm going to have to query something,
‫right? And then I'm going to return something, right? ‫So return peak rainfall at latitude I since time t.
‫What do I care about ‫in a particular query? ‫I only care about all ‫the things at I, right?
‫At a latitude I. ‫So really,
‫this isn't such an interesting thing, but I want to be able to ‫have maybe many data structures, one associated with each I.
‫Does that make sense? ‫Right? And how can I find ‫one in each I, right? ‫Quickly?
‫Put it in a dictionary. ‫What's my time bound?
‫Worst case log n, right? So what data ‫structure do I use for that set data structure?
‫A set AVO, right? So we're ‫going to first have a set AVO, ‫say, ‫I, ‫mapping latitudes to,
‫well, now we have more ‫data structures, right?
‫So we're going to store a lot of the things that have ‫the same latitudes in another data structure, right?
‫The one's probably ‫storing the times and the ‫rainfalls of all those measurements. ‫Yeah?
‫Yeah? A hash table?
‫A hash table. OK. So what kinds of query am I going ‫to want to do on the things at the same latitude?
‫You're going to want ‫to get the times. ‫I'm going to want to get ‫the times, but more than that,
‫I'm doing kind of an ordered query, right? I ‫need the things less than a certain time, right?
‫Greater.
‫Also, it's really worth. ELIZABETH NOLAN - Just a second. ‫Do you do like an AVL for the time and an AVL for the rain?
‫ELIZABETH NOLAN - OK. ‫Do I care about an ‫AVL for the rain? ‫Am I looking up on the rainfall?
‫No. ‫So I'm going to go ahead and ‫store these things in a time ‫sorted AVL, right, ‫to
‫mapping latitude I
‫to I'm going to call this data structure a ‫time data structure, right? I'm going to say
‫it's t of I. ‫OK?
‫That kind of looks like a recurrence, so it's a little ‫irking me right now, but I don't have anything better.
‫All right. So now each one of these ‫time data structures, right, is a set AVL
‫mapping time to the ‫rainfall measurement. Right? ‫All right.
‫So that's going to, if my query ‫was return the peak rainfall,
‫sorry, return the rainfall of the ‫thing with latitude I and time t,
‫we'd be done, kind of, right? You'd ‫know how to support that query, right?
‫To insert things, I insert things into ‫both data structures. I just look it up, ‫right?
‫The one complication here is ‫that I'm not asking for what ‫is the rainfall at ‫a particular time.
‫I want to know what the maximum ‫rainfall is up to this time. ‫OK.
‫So max heap's good if I ‫want to know the global max, ‫right? ‫But here, I want to know the max
‫bounded by a certain range. ‫OK?
‫So we're going to, you can ask me questions after ‫this. We're running out of time a little bit.
‫OK? ‫So anyone have an ‫idea for how, yeah?
‫OK. And then you can just look at the right child, and then just look at the max of that child. ‫JASON KUO - OK. So what your colleague is saying, if we augment by the max r in my subtree,
‫maybe we can use that ‫to figure out this query,
‫right, because we're ordered on t, right? We have this nice ‫monotonic property that everything that's going to be in my query,
‫right, everything to the right of a ‫certain time, right, if my time is above t,
‫right, at a particular node, then everything in the right subtree is also above that t, ‫right, because of the order of my set's data structure, right, because I'm ordered on times,
‫right? So there's maybe the possibility that if I look to my right subtree, I can not do work ‫all over here by just looking at the max in that subtree, right? So that's an idea of, let's say,
‫augmented. ‫JASON KUO - OK.
‫You probably want to give this a name ‫as well, right? So like v max, right,
‫where v is a node ‫in my thing, right?
‫And I want to show how to support this, right, ‫how I can compute that from its children.
‫So how do I actually ‫support this query, ‫right? ‫I can think of it recursively, ‫right?
‫I have a couple cases. ‫If I'm at a v here,
‫I want to define a recursive ‫function that's called peak
‫rainfall of a given node ‫lower bounded by a t, OK? ‫So if I'm here, ‫there's two cases, ‫right?
‫Either my time is bigger or smaller, ‫is in my range or out of my range, right?
‫If it's out of my range, ‫what do I do, right? ‫It's lower than my time bound.
‫I can just recursively call this function ‫on this node, right, because I know that any
‫thing is going to be down ‫here that I care about, right?
‫And that's just one recursive call down the tree, right? And so if I only limit ‫myself to one recursive call down the tree, I'm always going down each time.
‫This is going to take logarithmic time, right? OK, ‫so that's the first case. That's the easy case,
‫right? This thing ‫is not in range. ‫I return recursively ‫the thing to my right.
‫What's the other case? ‫I'm in my range, ‫right?
‫Well, now I could return ‫recursively call both sides, ‫right?
‫Because that's what this peak is ‫talking about. What's my peak rainfall?
‫But if I do that, if I call it here recursively and I call it here recursively, ‫that could take linear time, right? I might touch every node in my tree.
‫So why did I do this augmentation? So ‫I don't have to do work on this node.
‫I can just return the maximum ‫rainfall in this subtree, right, ‫and then recurse on this side.
‫So I did constant ‫work on this side.
‫I did one recursive call down ‫here, which could go to the bottom.
‫But that's OK. I can afford ‫to go to the bottom of the tree.
‫Does that make sense? And if ‫I don't have either subtree, ‫then I'm done. Right?
‫If at any time I don't have the node that ‫I'm supposed to recurse on, I take the max of
‫this subtree
‫myself and whatever the recursive return value is ‫here. I'm comparing three values returning their max.
‫Does that make sense? ‫OK, so that's what we call ‫a one -sided range query.
‫So in the, I think, problem session 4 that I didn't get to, ‫it shows you a way to do this for a two -sided range query,
‫where I need to know the maximum of ‫all things between two things, right?
‫But it's really no more difficult than this, defining ‫a recursive function that uses an augmentation
‫so that you don't have to do ‫recursive call on both sides. ‫Does that make sense? ‫OK,
‫that's going to be it for now. ‫And I can take questions after. ‫OK, thanks for coming.